<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-dots-signal-channel-10"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="DOTS Signal Channel">Distributed Denial-of-Service Open
    Threat Signaling (DOTS) Signal Channel</title>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization abbrev="McAfee">McAfee, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Embassy Golf Link Business Park</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560071</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>kondtir@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Prashanth Patil" initials="P." surname="Patil">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <email>praspati@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Andrew Mortensen" initials="A." surname="Mortensen">
      <organization>Arbor Networks, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2727 S. State St</street>

          <city>Ann Arbor, MI</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>48104</code>

          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>

        <email>amortensen@arbor.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Nik Teague" initials="N." surname="Teague">
      <organization>Verisign, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>

        <email>nteague@verisign.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <workgroup>DOTS</workgroup>

    <keyword>security</keyword>

    <keyword>mitigation</keyword>

    <keyword>service delivery</keyword>

    <keyword>connectivity</keyword>

    <keyword>anti-DDoS</keyword>

    <keyword>automation</keyword>

    <keyword>cooperation</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies the DOTS signal channel, a protocol for
      signaling the need for protection against Distributed Denial-of-Service
      (DDoS) attacks to a server capable of enabling network traffic
      mitigation on behalf of the requesting client.</t>

      <t>A companion document defines the DOTS data channel, a separate
      reliable communication layer for DOTS management and configuration.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Editorial Note (To be removed by RFC Editor)">
      <t>Please update these statements with the RFC number to be assigned to
      this document:<list style="symbols">
          <t>"This version of this YANG module is part of RFC XXXX;"</t>

          <t>"RFC XXXX: Distributed Denial-of-Service Open Threat Signaling
          (DOTS) Signal Channel";</t>

          <t>"| 3.00 | Alternate server | [RFCXXXX] |"</t>

          <t>reference: RFC XXXX</t>
        </list></t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>A distributed denial-of-service (DDoS) attack is an attempt to make
      machines or network resources unavailable to their intended users. In
      most cases, sufficient scale can be achieved by compromising enough
      end-hosts and using those infected hosts to perpetrate and amplify the
      attack. The victim in this attack can be an application server, a host,
      a router, a firewall, or an entire network.</t>

      <t>Network applications have finite resources like CPU cycles, number of
      processes or threads they can create and use, maximum number of
      simultaneous connections it can handle, limited resources of the control
      plane, etc. When processing network traffic, such applications are
      supposed to use these resources to offer the intended task in the most
      efficient fashion. However, a DDoS attacker may be able to prevent an
      application from performing its intended task by causing the application
      to exhaust the finite supply of a specific resource.</t>

      <t>TCP DDoS SYN-flood, for example, is a memory-exhaustion attack on the
      victim and ACK-flood is a CPU exhaustion attack on the victim <xref
      target="RFC4987"></xref>. Attacks on the link are carried out by sending
      enough traffic such that the link becomes excessively congested, and
      legitimate traffic suffers high packet loss. Stateful firewalls can also
      be attacked by sending traffic that causes the firewall to hold
      excessive state. The firewall then runs out of memory, and can no longer
      instantiate the state required to pass legitimate flows. Other possible
      DDoS attacks are discussed in <xref target="RFC4732"></xref>.</t>

      <t>In many cases, it may not be possible for network administrators to
      determine the causes of an attack, but instead just realize that certain
      resources seem to be under attack. This document defines a lightweight
      protocol permitting a DOTS client to request mitigation from one or more
      DOTS servers for protection against detected, suspected, or anticipated
      attacks. This protocol enables cooperation between DOTS agents to permit
      a highly-automated network defense that is robust, reliable and
      secure.</t>

      <t>An example of network diagram showing a deployment of DOTS agents is
      shown in <xref target="fig1"></xref>. In this example, the DOTS server
      is operating on the access network.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="fig1" title="Sample DOTS Deployment (1)">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[   
   Network                                           
   Resource         CPE router            Access network     __________      
 +-----------+    +--------------+       +-------------+    /          \   
 |           |____|              |_______|             |___ | Internet |
 |DOTS client|    | DOTS gateway |       | DOTS server |    |          |
 |           |    |              |       |             |    |          |
 +-----------+    +--------------+       +-------------+    \__________/]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>The DOTS server can also be running on the Internet, as depicted in
      <xref target="fig_blah"></xref>.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="fig_blah" title="Sample DOTS Deployment (2)">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[   
  Network                                               DDoS mitigation  
  Resource        CPE router             __________         service
 +-----------+    +-------------+       /          \    +-------------+
 |           |____|             |_______|          |___ |             |
 |DOTS client|    |DOTS gateway |       | Internet |    | DOTS server |
 |           |    |             |       |          |    |             |
 +-----------+    +-------------+       \__________/    +-------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>In typical deployments, the DOTS client belongs to a
      different administrative domain than the DOTS server. For example, the
      DOTS client is a firewall protecting services owned and operated by an
      domain, while the DOTS server is owned and operated by a different
      domain providing DDoS mitigation services. That domain providing DDoS
      mitigation service might, or might not, also provide Internet access
      service to the website operator.</t>

      <t>The DOTS server may (not) be co-located with the DOTS mitigator. In
      typical deployments, the DOTS server belongs to the same administrative
      domain as the mitigator. The DOTS client can communicate directly with
      the DOTS server or indirectly via a DOTS gateway.</t>

      <t>The document adheres to the DOTS architecture <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dots-architecture"></xref>. The requirements for DOTS
      signal channel protocol are obtained from <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"></xref>. This document satisfies all
      the use cases discussed in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dots-use-cases"></xref>.</t>

      <t>This document focuses on the DOTS signal channel. This is a companion
      document to the DOTS data channel specification <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dots-data-channel"></xref> that defines a configuration
      and bulk data exchange mechanism supporting the DOTS signal channel.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="notation" title="Notational Conventions and Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>

      <t>(D)TLS: For brevity this term is used for statements that apply to
      both Transport Layer Security <xref target="RFC5246"></xref> and
      Datagram Transport Layer Security <xref target="RFC6347"></xref>.
      Specific terms will be used for any statement that applies to either
      protocol alone.</t>

      <t>The reader should be familiar with the terms defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dots-architecture"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The meaning of the symbols in YANG tree diagrams is defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-netmod-yang-tree-diagrams"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Design Overview">
      <t>The DOTS signal channel is built on top of the Constrained
      Application Protocol (CoAP) <xref target="RFC7252"></xref>, a
      lightweight protocol originally designed for constrained devices and
      networks. CoAP&rsquo;s expectation of packet loss, support for
      asynchronous non-confirmable messaging, congestion control, small
      message overhead limiting the need for fragmentation, use of minimal
      resources, and support for (D)TLS make it a good foundation on which to
      build the DOTS signaling mechanism.</t>

      <t>The DOTS signal channel is layered on existing standards (<xref
      target="fig_dots"></xref>).</t>

      <t><figure anchor="fig_dots"
          title="Abstract Layering of DOTS signal channel over CoAP over (D)TLS">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[          +--------------+
          |     DOTS     |
          +--------------+
          |     CoAP     |
          +--------------+
          | TLS  | DTLS  |
          +--------------+
          | TCP  |  UDP  |
          +--------------+
          |      IP      |
          +--------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>By default, DOTS signal channel MUST run over port number TBD as
      defined in <xref target="port"></xref>, for both UDP and TCP, unless the
      DOTS server has mutual agreement with its DOTS clients to use a port
      other than TBD for DOTS signal channel, or DOTS clients supports means
      to dynamically discover the ports used by their DOTS servers. In order
      to use a distinct port number (vs. TBD), DOTS clients and servers should
      support a configurable parameter to supply the port number to use.</t>

      <t>The signal channel is initiated by the DOTS client (<xref
      target="m_req"></xref>). Once the signal channel is established, the
      DOTS agents periodically send heartbeats to keep the channel active
      (<xref target="hb"></xref>). At any time, the DOTS client may send a
      mitigation request message to a DOTS server over the active channel.
      While mitigation is active, due to the higher likelihood of packet loss
      during a DDoS attack, the DOTS server periodically sends status messages
      to the client, including basic mitigation feedback details. Mitigation
      remains active until the DOTS client explicitly terminates mitigation,
      or the mitigation lifetime expires.</t>

      <t>DOTS signaling can happen with DTLS <xref target="RFC6347"></xref>
      over UDP and TLS <xref target="RFC5246"></xref> over TCP. Likewise,
      requests may be sent using IPv4 or IPv6 transfer capabilities. A Happy
      Eyeballs procedure for DOTS signal channel is specified in <xref
      target="HE"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Messages exchanged between DOTS clients and servers are serialized
      using Concise Binary Object Representation (CBOR) <xref
      target="RFC7049"></xref>, CBOR is a binary encoding designed for small
      code and message size. CBOR encoded payloads are used to convey signal
      channel specific payload messages that convey request parameters and
      response information such as errors. This specification uses the
      encoding rules defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-yang-cbor"></xref>
      for representing mitigation scope and DOTS signal channel session
      configuration data defined using YANG (<xref target="YANG"></xref>) as
      CBOR data.</t>

      <t>In order to prevent fragmentation, DOTS agents must follow the
      recommendations in Section 4.6 of <xref target="RFC7252"></xref>. Refer
      to <xref target="mtu"></xref> for more details.</t>

      <t>DOTS agents MUST support GET, PUT, and DELETE CoAP methods. The
      payload included in CoAP responses with 2.xx and 3.xx Response Codes
      MUST be of content type "application/cbor" (Section 5.5.1 of <xref
      target="RFC7252"></xref>). CoAP responses with 4.xx and 5.xx error
      Response Codes MUST include a diagnostic payload (Section 5.5.2 of <xref
      target="RFC7252"></xref>). The Diagnostic Payload may contain additional
      information to aid troubleshooting.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="DOTS Signal Channel: Messages &amp; Behaviors">
      <section title="DOTS Server(s) Discovery">
        <t>This document assumes that DOTS clients are provisioned with the
        reachability information of their DOTS server(s) using a variety of
        means (e.g., local configuration, or dynamic means such as DHCP).
        These means are out of scope of this document.</t>

        <t>Likewise, it is out of scope of this document to specify the
        behavior to follow by a DOTS client to place its requests (e.g.,
        contact all servers, select one server among the list) when multiple
        DOTS servers are provisioned.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="CoAP URIs">
        <t>The DOTS server MUST support the use of the path-prefix of "/.well-
        known/" as defined in <xref target="RFC5785"></xref> and the
        registered name of "dots". Each DOTS operation is indicated by a
        path-suffix that indicates the intended operation.</t>

        <texttable align="center" anchor="uris" style="all"
                   title="Operations and their corresponding URIs">
          <ttcol>Operation</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Operation path</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Details</ttcol>

          <c>Mitigation</c>

          <c>/v1/mitigate</c>

          <c><xref target="m_req"></xref></c>

          <c>Session configuration</c>

          <c>/v1/config</c>

          <c><xref target="sigconfig"></xref></c>
        </texttable>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="HE" title="Happy Eyeballs for DOTS Signal Channel">
        <t>DOTS signaling can happen with DTLS over UDP and TLS over TCP. A
        DOTS client can use DNS to determine the IP address(es) of a DOTS
        server or a DOTS client may be provided with the list of DOTS server
        IP addresses. The DOTS client MUST know a DOTS server's domain name;
        hard-coding the domain name of the DOTS server into software is NOT
        RECOMMENDED in case the domain name is not valid or needs to change
        for legal or other reasons. The DOTS client performs A and/or AAAA
        record lookup of the domain name and the result will be a list of IP
        addresses, each of which can be used to contact the DOTS server using
        UDP and TCP.</t>

        <t>If an IPv4 path to reach a DOTS server is found, but the DOTS
        server's IPv6 path is not working, a dual-stack DOTS client can
        experience a significant connection delay compared to an IPv4-only
        DOTS client. The other problem is that if a middlebox between the DOTS
        client and DOTS server is configured to block UDP, the DOTS client
        will fail to establish a DTLS session with the DOTS server and will,
        then, have to fall back to TLS over TCP incurring significant
        connection delays. <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"></xref>
        discusses that DOTS client and server will have to support both
        connectionless and connection-oriented protocols.</t>

        <t>To overcome these connection setup problems, the DOTS client can
        try connecting to the DOTS server using both IPv6 and IPv4, and try
        both DTLS over UDP and TLS over TCP in a fashion similar to the Happy
        Eyeballs mechanism <xref target="RFC6555"></xref>. These connection
        attempts are performed by the DOTS client when its initializes, and
        the client uses that information for its subsequent alert to the DOTS
        server. In order of preference (most preferred first), it is UDP over
        IPv6, UDP over IPv4, TCP over IPv6, and finally TCP over IPv4, which
        adheres to <xref target="RFC6724">address preference order</xref> and
        the DOTS preference that UDP be used over TCP (to avoid TCP's head of
        line blocking).</t>

        <t><figure anchor="fig_happy_eyeballs" title="DOTS Happy Eyeballs">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
DOTS client                                               DOTS server
   |                                                         |
   |--DTLS ClientHello, IPv6 ---->X                          |
   |--TCP SYN, IPv6-------------->X                          |
   |--DTLS ClientHello, IPv4 ---->X                          |
   |--TCP SYN, IPv4----------------------------------------->|
   |--DTLS ClientHello, IPv6 ---->X                          |    
   |--TCP SYN, IPv6-------------->X                          |
   |<-TCP SYNACK---------------------------------------------|
   |--DTLS ClientHello, IPv4 ---->X                          |
   |--TCP ACK----------------------------------------------->|
   |<------------Establish TLS Session---------------------->|
   |----------------DOTS signal----------------------------->|
   |                                                         |
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>In reference to <xref target="fig_happy_eyeballs"></xref>, the DOTS
        client sends two TCP SYNs and two DTLS ClientHello messages at the
        same time over IPv6 and IPv4. In this example, it is assumed that the
        IPv6 path is broken and UDP is dropped by a middlebox but has little
        impact to the DOTS client because there is no long delay before using
        IPv4 and TCP. The DOTS client repeats the mechanism to discover if
        DOTS signaling with DTLS over UDP becomes available from the DOTS
        server, so the DOTS client can migrate the DOTS signal channel from
        TCP to UDP, but such probing SHOULD NOT be done more frequently than
        every 24 hours and MUST NOT be done more frequently than every 5
        minutes.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="m_req" title="DOTS Mitigation Methods">
        <t>The following methods are used by a DOTS client to request,
        withdraw, or retrieve the status of mitigation requests:<list
            style="hanging">
            <t hangText="PUT:">DOTS clients use the PUT method to request
            mitigation from a DOTS server (<xref target="post"></xref>).
            During active mitigation, DOTS clients may use PUT requests to
            convey mitigation efficacy updates to the DOTS server (<xref
            target="put"></xref>).</t>

            <t hangText="DELETE:">DOTS clients use the DELETE method to
            withdraw a request for mitigation from the DOTS server (<xref
            target="del"></xref>).</t>

            <t hangText="GET:">DOTS clients may use the GET method to
            subscribe to DOTS server status messages, or to retrieve the list
            of existing mitigations (<xref target="get"></xref>).</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Mitigation request and response messages are marked as
        Non-confirmable messages. DOTS agents SHOULD follow the data
        transmission guidelines discussed in Section 3.1.3 of <xref
        target="RFC8085"></xref> and control transmission behavior by not
        sending on average more than one UDP datagram per RTT to the peer DOTS
        agent.</t>

        <t>Requests marked by the DOTS client as Non-confirmable messages are
        sent at regular intervals until a response is received from the DOTS
        server. If the DOTS client cannot maintain an RTT estimate, it SHOULD
        NOT send more than one Non-confirmable request every 3 seconds, and
        SHOULD use an even less aggressive rate when possible (case 2 in
        Section 3.1.3 of <xref target="RFC8085"></xref>).</t>

        <section anchor="post" title="Request Mitigation">
          <t>When a DOTS client requires mitigation for any reason, the DOTS
          client uses CoAP PUT method to send a mitigation request to the DOTS
          server(s) (<xref target="Figure1"></xref>, illustrated in JSON
          diagnostic notation). If this DOTS client is entitled to solicit the
          DOTS service, the DOTS server can enable mitigation on behalf of the
          DOTS client by communicating the DOTS client's request to the
          mitigator and relaying selected mitigator feedback to the requesting
          DOTS client.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="Figure1" title="PUT to convey DOTS signals">
              <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[  Header: PUT (Code=0.03)
  Uri-Host: "host" 
  Uri-Path: ".well-known"
  Uri-Path: "dots"
  Uri-Path: "version"
  Uri-Path: "mitigate"
  Content-Type: "application/cbor"
  {
    "mitigation-scope": {
      "client-identifier": [
         "string"
      ],
      "scope": [
        {
          "mitigation-id": integer,  
          "target-ip": [
             "string"
           ],
          "target-prefix": [
             "string"
           ],
          "target-port-range": [
             {
               "lower-port": integer,
               "upper-port": integer
             }
           ],     
           "target-protocol": [
             integer
           ],
           "target-fqdn": [
             "string"
           ],
           "target-uri": [
             "string"
           ],
           "alias-name": [
             "string"
           ],
          "lifetime": integer
        }
      ]
    }
  }
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>The parameters are described below:</t>

          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="client-identifier:">The client identifier MAY be
              conveyed by the DOTS gateway to propagate the DOTS client
              identity from the gateway's client-side to the gateway's
              server-side, and from the gateway's server-side to the DOTS
              server. This allows the final DOTS server to accept mitigation
              requests with scopes which the DOTS client is authorized to
              manage. <vspace blankLines="1" />The 'client-identifier' value
              MUST be assigned by the DOTS gateway in a manner that ensures
              that there is no probability that the same value will be
              assigned to a different DOTS client. The DOTS gateway MUST
              obscure potentially sensitive DOTS client identity information.
              The client-identifier attribute SHOULD NOT to be generated and
              included by the DOTS client. <vspace blankLines="1" />This is an
              optional attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="mitigation-id:">Identifier for the mitigation
              request represented using an integer. This identifier MUST be
              unique for each mitigation request bound to the DOTS client,
              i.e., the mitigation-id parameter value in the mitigation
              request needs to be unique relative to the mitigation-id
              parameter values of active mitigation requests conveyed from the
              DOTS client to the DOTS server. This identifier MUST be
              generated by the DOTS client. This document does not make any
              assumption about how this identifier is generated. This is a
              mandatory attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="target-ip:">A list of IP addresses under attack.
              This is an optional attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="target-prefix:">A list of prefixes under attack.
              Prefixes are represented using CIDR notation <xref
              target="RFC4632"></xref>. This is an optional attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="target-port-range:">A list of ports under attack.
              The port range, lower-port for lower port number and upper-port
              for upper port number. When only lower-port is present, it
              represents a single port. For TCP, UDP, Stream Control
              Transmission Protocol (SCTP) <xref target="RFC4960"></xref>, or
              Datagram Congestion Control Protocol (DCCP) <xref
              target="RFC4340"></xref>: the range of ports (e.g., 1024-65535).
              This is an optional attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="target-protocol:">A list of protocols under attack.
              Values are taken from the IANA protocol registry <xref
              target="proto_numbers"></xref>. The value 0 has a special
              meaning for 'all protocols'. This is an optional attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="target-fqdn: ">A list of Fully Qualified Domain
              Names. Fully Qualified Domain Name (FQDN) is the full name of a
              system, rather than just its hostname. For example, "venera" is
              a hostname, and "venera.isi.edu" is an FQDN. This is an optional
              attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="target-uri: ">A list of Uniform Resource
              Identifiers (URI). This is an optional attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="alias-name:">A list of aliases. Aliases can be
              created using the DOTS data channel (Section 3.1.1 of <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-dots-data-channel"></xref>) or direct
              configuration, or other means and then used in subsequent signal
              channel exchanges to refer more efficiently to the resources
              under attack. This is an optional attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="lifetime: ">Lifetime of the mitigation request in
              seconds. The RECOMMENDED lifetime of a mitigation request is
              3600 seconds (60 minutes) -- this value was chosen to be long
              enough so that refreshing is not typically a burden on the DOTS
              client, while expiring the request where the client has
              unexpectedly quit in a timely manner. <vspace blankLines="1" />A
              lifetime of negative one (-1) indicates indefinite lifetime for
              the mitigation request. A lifetime of 0 in the request is an
              invalid value.<vspace blankLines="1" />DOTS clients MUST include
              this parameter in their mitigation requests. Upon the expiry of
              this lifetime, and if the request is not refreshed, the
              mitigation request is removed. The request can be refreshed by
              sending the same request again. The server MAY refuse indefinite
              lifetime, for policy reasons; the granted lifetime value is
              returned in the response. DOTS clients MUST be prepared to not
              be granted mitigations with indefinite lifetimes. The server
              MUST always indicate the actual lifetime in the response and the
              remaining lifetime in status messages sent to the client. This
              is a mandatory attribute.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The CBOR key values for the parameters are defined in <xref
          target="mapping"></xref>. <xref target="IANA"></xref> defines how
          the CBOR key values can be allocated to standards bodies and
          vendors.</t>

          <t>FQDN and URI mitigation scopes may be thought of as a form of
          scope alias, in which the addresses to which the domain name or URI
          resolve represent the full scope of the mitigation.</t>

          <t>In the PUT request at least one of the attributes 'target-ip' or
          'target-prefix' or 'target-fqdn' or 'target-uri 'or 'alias-name'
          MUST be present. If the attribute value is empty, then the attribute
          MUST NOT be present in the request. DOTS agents can safely ignore
          Vendor-Specific parameters they don't understand.</t>

          <t>The relative order of two mitigation requests from a DOTS client
          is determined by comparing their respective 'mitigation-id' values.
          If two mitigation requests have overlapping mitigation scopes, the
          mitigation request with higher numeric 'mitigation-id' value will
          override the mitigation request with a lower numeric 'mitigation-id'
          value. Two mitigation-ids from a DOTS client are overlapping if
          there is a common IP address, IP prefix, FQDN, URI, or alias-name.
          To avoid maintaining a long list of overlapping mitigation requests
          from a DOTS client and avoid error-prone provisioning of mitigation
          requests from a DOTS client, the overlapped lower numeric
          'mitigation-id' MUST be automatically deleted and no longer
          available at the DOTS server.</t>

          <t>The Uri-Path option carries a major and minor version
          nomenclature to manage versioning and DOTS signal channel in this
          specification uses v1 major version.</t>

          <t>If the DOTS client is using the certificate provisioned by the
          Enrollment over Secure Transport (EST) server <xref
          target="RFC7030"></xref> in the DOTS gateway-domain to authenticate
          itself to the DOTS gateway, then the 'client-identifier' value can
          be the output of a cryptographic hash algorithm whose input is the
          DER-encoded ASN.1 representation of the Subject Public Key Info
          (SPKI) of an X.509 certificate. In this version of the
          specification, the cryptographic hash algorithm used is SHA-256
          <xref target="RFC6234"></xref>. The output of the cryptographic hash
          algorithm is truncated to 16 bytes; truncation is done by stripping
          off the final 16 bytes. The truncated output is base64url encoded.
          If the 'client-identifier' value is already present in the
          mitigation request received from the DOTS client, the DOTS gateway
          MAY compute the 'client-identifier' value, as discussed above, and
          add the computed 'client-identifier' value to the end of the
          'client-identifier' list. The DOTS server MUST NOT use the
          &lsquo;client-identifier&rsquo; for the DOTS client authentication
          process.</t>

          <t>In both DOTS signal and data channel sessions, the DOTS client
          MUST authenticate itself to the DOTS server (<xref
          target="mutauth"></xref>). The DOTS server may use the algorithm in
          Section 7 of <xref target="RFC7589"></xref> to derive the DOTS
          client identity or username from the client certificate. The DOTS
          client identity allows the DOTS server to accept mitigation requests
          with scopes which the DOTS client is authorized to manage. The DOTS
          server couples the DOTS signal and data channel sessions using the
          DOTS client identity and the 'client-identifier' parameter value, so
          the DOTS server can validate whether the aliases conveyed in the
          mitigation request were indeed created by the same DOTS client using
          the DOTS data channel session. If the aliases were not created by
          the DOTS client, the DOTS server returns 4.00 (Bad Request) in the
          response.</t>

          <t>The DOTS server couples the DOTS signal channel sessions using
          the DOTS client identity and the 'client-identifier' parameter
          value, and the DOTS server uses 'mitigation-id' parameter value to
          detect duplicate mitigation requests. If the mitigation request
          contains both alias-name and other parameters identifying the target
          resources (such as, 'target-ip', 'target-prefix',
          'target-port-range', 'target-fqdn', or 'target-uri'), then the DOTS
          server appends the parameter values in 'alias-name' with the
          corresponding parameter values in 'target-ip', 'target-prefix',
          'target-port-range', 'target-fqdn', or 'target-uri'.</t>

          <t><xref target="Figure2"></xref> shows a PUT request example to
          signal that ports 80, 8080, and 443 on the servers 2001:db8:6401::1
          and 2001:db8:6401::2 are being attacked (illustrated in JSON
          diagnostic notation).</t>

          <t><figure anchor="Figure2" title="PUT for DOTS signal">
              <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[  Header: PUT (Code=0.03)
  Uri-Host: "www.example.com" 
  Uri-Path: ".well-known"
  Uri-Path: "dots"
  Uri-Path: "v1"
  Uri-Path: "mitigate"
  Content-Format: "application/cbor"
  {
    "mitigation-scope": {
      "client-identifier": [
         "dz6pHjaADkaFTbjr0JGBpw"
      ],
      "scope": [
        {
          "mitigation-id": 12332,  
          "target-ip": [
             "2001:db8:6401::1",
             "2001:db8:6401::2"
           ],
          "target-port-range": [
            { 
              "lower-port": 80
            },
            { 
              "lower-port": 443 
            },
            { 
               "lower-port": 8080
            }
           ],     
           "target-protocol": [
             6
           ]
        }
      ]
    }
  }

The CBOR encoding format is shown below:

A1                                      # map(1)
   01                                   # unsigned(1)
   A2                                   # map(2)
      18 20                             # unsigned(32)
      81                                # array(1)
      76                                # text(22)
         647A3670486A6141446B614654626A72304A47427077 # "dz6pHjaADkaFTbjr0JGBpw"
      02                                # unsigned(2)
      81                                # array(1)
         A4                             # map(4)
            03                          # unsigned(3)
            19 302C                     # unsigned(12332)
            04                          # unsigned(4)
            82                          # array(2)
               70                       # text(16)
                  323030313A6462383A363430313A3A31 # "2001:db8:6401::1"
               70                       # text(16)
                  323030313A6462383A363430313A3A32 # "2001:db8:6401::2"
            05                          # unsigned(5)
            83                          # array(3)
               A1                       # map(1)
                  06                    # unsigned(6)
                  18 50                 # unsigned(80)
               A1                       # map(1)
                  06                    # unsigned(6)
                  19 01BB               # unsigned(443)
               A1                       # map(1)
                  06                    # unsigned(6)
                  19 1F90               # unsigned(8080)
            08                          # unsigned(8)
            81                          # array(1)
               06                       # unsigned(6)

]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>The DOTS server indicates the result of processing the PUT
          request using CoAP response codes. CoAP 2.xx codes are success. CoAP
          4.xx codes are some sort of invalid requests (client errors). COAP
          5.xx codes are returned if the DOTS server has erred or is currently
          unavailable to provide mitigation in response to the mitigation
          request from the DOTS client.</t>

          <t><xref target="put_response"></xref> shows an example of a PUT
          request that is successfully processed (i.e., CoAP 2.xx response
          codes).</t>

          <t><figure anchor="put_response" title="2.xx response body">
              <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[{
  "mitigation-scope": {
     "client-identifier": [
         "string"
     ],
     "scope": [
        {
          "mitigation-id": integer,
          "lifetime": integer
        }
      ]
   }
}
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>If the DOTS server does not find the 'mitigation-id' parameter
          value conveyed in the PUT request in its configuration data, then
          the server MAY accept the mitigation request by sending back a 2.01
          (Created) response to the DOTS client; the DOTS server will
          consequently try to mitigate the attack.</t>

          <t>If the DOTS server finds the 'mitigation-id' parameter value
          conveyed in the PUT request in its configuration data, then the
          server MAY update the mitigation request, and a 2.04 (Changed)
          response is returned to indicate a successful update of the
          mitigation request.</t>

          <t>If the request is missing one or more mandatory attributes, then
          4.00 (Bad Request) will be returned in the response or if the
          request contains invalid or unknown parameters then 4.02 (Invalid
          query) is returned in the response.</t>

          <t>For a mitigation request to continue beyond the initial
          negotiated lifetime, the DOTS client need to refresh the current
          mitigation request by sending a new PUT request. The PUT request
          MUST use the same 'mitigation-id' value, and MUST repeat all the
          other parameters as sent in the original mitigation request apart
          from a possible change to the lifetime parameter value.</t>

          <t>A DOTS gateway MUST update the &lsquo;client-identifier&rsquo;
          list in the response to remove the 'client-identifier' value it had
          added in the corresponding request before forwarding the response to
          the DOTS client.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="del" title="Withdraw a Mitigation">
          <t>A DELETE request is used to withdraw a DOTS mitigation request
          from a DOTS server (<xref target="Figure3"></xref>).</t>

          <figure anchor="Figure3" title="Withdraw DOTS signal">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[  Header: DELETE (Code=0.04)
  Uri-Host: "host" 
  Uri-Path: ".well-known"
  Uri-Path: "dots"
  Uri-Path: "version"
  Uri-Path: "mitigate"
  Content-Format: "application/cbor"
  {
    "mitigation-scope": {
      "client-identifier": [
         "string"
      ],
      "scope": [
        {
          "mitigation-id": integer
        }
      ] 
    }     
  }
]]></artwork>
          </figure>

          <t></t>

          <t>The DOTS server immediately acknowledges a DOTS client's request
          to withdraw the DOTS signal using 2.02 (Deleted) response code with
          no response payload. A 2.02 (Deleted) Response Code is returned even
          if the 'mitigation-id' parameter value conveyed in the DELETE
          request does not exist in its configuration data before the
          request.</t>

          <t>If the DOTS server finds the 'mitigation-id' parameter value
          conveyed in the DELETE request in its configuration data, then to
          protect against route or DNS flapping caused by a client rapidly
          toggling mitigation, and to dampen the effect of oscillating
          attacks, DOTS servers MAY allow mitigation to continue for a limited
          period after acknowledging a DOTS client's withdrawal of a
          mitigation request. During this period, the DOTS server status
          messages SHOULD indicate that mitigation is active but terminating.
          The initial active-but-terminating period SHOULD be sufficiently
          long to absorb latency incurred by route propagation. The
          active-but-terminating period SHOULD be set by default to 120
          seconds. If the client requests mitigation again before the initial
          active-but-terminating period elapses, the DOTS server MAY
          exponentially increase the active-but- terminating period up to a
          maximum of 300 seconds (5 minutes). After the active-but-terminating
          period elapses, the DOTS server MUST treat the mitigation as
          terminated, as the DOTS client is no longer responsible for the
          mitigation. For example, if there is a financial relationship
          between the DOTS client and server domains, the DOTS client ceases
          incurring cost at this point.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="get"
                 title="Retrieve Information Related to a Mitigation">
          <t>A GET request is used to retrieve information (including status)
          of a DOTS mitigation from a DOTS server (<xref
          target="Figure4"></xref>). If the DOTS server does not find the
          'mitigation-id' parameter value conveyed in the GET request in its
          configuration data, then it responds with a 4.04 (Not Found) error
          response code. The 'c' (content) parameter and its permitted values
          defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-comi"></xref> can be used to
          retrieve non-configuration data (attack mitigation status) or
          configuration data or both. The DOTS server SHOULD support this
          optional filtering capability but can safely ignore it if not
          supported.</t>

          <t>The examples depicted in <xref target="Figure4"></xref> assume
          the default of "c=a".</t>

          <figure anchor="Figure4" title="GET to retrieve the rules">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[1) To retrieve all DOTS signals signaled by the DOTS client.
  
  Header: GET (Code=0.01)
  Uri-Host: "host" 
  Uri-Path: ".well-known"
  Uri-Path: "dots"
  Uri-Path: "version"
  Uri-Path: "mitigate"
  Observe : 0
  {
    "mitigation-scope": {
      "client-identifier": [
         "string"
      ]
    }     
  }

2) To retrieve a specific DOTS signal signaled by the DOTS client.
   The configuration data in the response will be formatted in the 
   same order it was processed at the DOTS server.
  
  Header: GET (Code=0.01)
  Uri-Host: "host" 
  Uri-Path: ".well-known"
  Uri-Path: "dots"
  Uri-Path: "version"
  Uri-Path: "mitigate"
  Observe : 0
  Content-Format: "application/cbor"
  {
    "mitigation-scope": {
      "client-identifier": [
         "string"
      ],
      "scope": [
        {
          "mitigation-id": integer
        }
      ] 
    }     
  }
]]></artwork>
          </figure>

          <t><xref target="Figure5"></xref> shows a response example of all
          the active mitigation requests associated with the DOTS client on
          the DOTS server and the mitigation status of each mitigation
          request.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="Figure5" title="Response body">
              <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[{
  "mitigation-scope": {
     "scope": [
        {
          "mitigation-id": 12332,  
          "mitigation-start": 1507818434.00,
          "target-protocol": [
              17
           ],
          "lifetime":1800,
          "status":2,
          "bytes-dropped": 134334555,
          "bps-dropped":  43344,
          "pkts-dropped": 333334444,
          "pps-dropped": 432432
         }, 
        {
          "mitigation-id": 12333,  
          "mitigation-start": 1507818393.00, 
          "target-protocol": [
              6
           ],
          "lifetime":1800,
          "status":3
          "bytes-dropped": 0,
          "bps-dropped":  0,
          "pkts-dropped": 0,
          "pps-dropped": 0
        }
     ]
  }
 }]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>The mitigation status parameters are described below.</t>

          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="lifetime:">The remaining lifetime of the mitigation
              request in seconds.</t>

              <t hangText="mitigation-start:">Mitigation start time is
              represented in seconds relative to 1970-01-01T00:00Z in UTC time
              (Section 2.4.1 of <xref target="RFC7049"></xref>). The encoding
              is modified so that the leading tag 1 (epoch-based date/time)
              MUST be omitted.</t>

              <t hangText="bytes-dropped:">The total dropped byte count for
              the mitigation request since the attack mitigation is triggered.
              The count wraps around when it reaches the maximum value of
              unsigned integer. This is an optional attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="bps-dropped:">The average dropped bytes per second
              for the mitigation request since the attack mitigation is
              triggered. This SHOULD be a five-minute average. This is an
              optional attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="pkts-dropped:">The total dropped packet count for
              the mitigation request since the attack mitigation is triggered.
              This is an optional attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="pps-dropped:">The average dropped packets per
              second for the mitigation request since the attack mitigation is
              triggered. This SHOULD be a five-minute average. This is an
              optional attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="status:">Status of attack mitigation. The 'status'
              parameter is a mandatory attribute.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The various possible values of 'status' parameter are explained
          in <xref target="status"></xref>.</t>

          <texttable anchor="status" style="all"
                     title=" Values of 'status' parameter">
            <ttcol align="right">Parameter value</ttcol>

            <ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>

            <c>1</c>

            <c>Attack mitigation is in progress (e.g., changing the network
            path to re-route the inbound traffic to DOTS mitigator).</c>

            <c>2</c>

            <c>Attack is successfully mitigated (e.g., traffic is redirected
            to a DDOS mitigator and attack traffic is dropped).</c>

            <c>3</c>

            <c>Attack has stopped and the DOTS client can withdraw the
            mitigation request.</c>

            <c>4</c>

            <c>Attack has exceeded the mitigation provider capability.</c>

            <c>5</c>

            <c>DOTS client has withdrawn the mitigation request and the
            mitigation is active but terminating.</c>

            <c>6</c>

            <c>The mitigation is now terminated.</c>
          </texttable>

          <t>The observe option defined in <xref target="RFC7641"></xref>
          extends the CoAP core protocol with a mechanism for a CoAP client to
          "observe" a resource on a CoAP server: the client retrieves a
          representation of the resource and requests this representation be
          updated by the server as long as the client is interested in the
          resource. A DOTS client conveys the observe option set to '0' in the
          GET request to receive unsolicited notifications of attack
          mitigation status from the DOTS server. Unidirectional notifications
          within the bidirectional signal channel allows unsolicited message
          delivery, enabling asynchronous notifications between the agents.
          Due to the higher likelihood of packet loss during a DDoS attack,
          DOTS server periodically sends attack mitigation status to the DOTS
          client and also notifies the DOTS client whenever the status of the
          attack mitigation changes. If the DOTS server cannot maintain a RTT
          estimate, it SHOULD NOT send more than one unsolicited notification
          every 3 seconds, and SHOULD use an even less aggressive rate when
          possible (case 2 in Section 3.1.3 of <xref
          target="RFC8085"></xref>).</t>

          <t>A DOTS client that is no longer interested in receiving
          notifications from the DOTS server can simply "forget" the
          observation. When the DOTS server then sends the next notification,
          the DOTS client will not recognize the token in the message and thus
          will return a Reset message. This causes the DOTS server to remove
          the associated entry. Alternatively, the DOTS client can explicitly
          deregister by issuing a GET request that has the Token field set to
          the token of the observation to be cancelled and includes an Observe
          Option with the value set to '1' (deregister).</t>

          <t><xref target="Figure6"></xref> shows an example of a DOTS client
          requesting a DOTS server to send notifications related a given
          mitigation request.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="Figure6"
              title="Notifications of attack mitigation status">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
DOTS Client                   DOTS Server
   |                               |
   |  GET /<mitigation-id number>  |
   |  Token: 0x4a                  |   Registration
   |  Observe: 0                   |
   +------------------------------>|
   |                               |
   |  2.05 Content                 |
   |  Token: 0x4a                  |   Notification of
   |  Observe: 12                  |   the current state
   |  status: "mitigation          |  
   |          in progress"         |
   |<------------------------------+
   |  2.05 Content                 |
   |  Token: 0x4a                  |   Notification upon
   |  Observe: 44                  |    a state change
   |  status: "mitigation          |  
   |          complete"            |
   |<------------------------------+
   |  2.05 Content                 |
   |  Token: 0x4a                  |   Notification upon
   |  Observe: 60                  |   a state change
   |  status: "attack stopped"     |  
   |<------------------------------+
   |                               |    ]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <section title="Mitigation Status">
            <t>The DOTS client can send the GET request at frequent intervals
            without the Observe option to retrieve the configuration data of
            the mitigation request and non-configuration data (i.e., the
            attack status). The frequency of polling the DOTS server to get
            the mitigation status should follow the transmission guidelines
            given in Section 3.1.3 of <xref target="RFC8085"></xref>. If the
            DOTS server has been able to mitigate the attack and the attack
            has stopped, the DOTS server indicates as such in the status, and
            the DOTS client recalls the mitigation request by issuing a DELETE
            for the mitigation-id.</t>

            <t>A DOTS client should react to the status of the attack from the
            DOTS server and not the fact that it has recognized, using its own
            means, that the attack has been mitigated. This ensures that the
            DOTS client does not recall a mitigation request in a premature
            fashion because it is possible that the DOTS client does not sense
            the DDOS attack on its resources but the DOTS server could be
            actively mitigating the attack and the attack is not completely
            averted.</t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="put" title="Efficacy Update from DOTS Clients">
          <t>While DDoS mitigation is active, due to the likelihood of packet
          loss, a DOTS client MAY periodically transmit DOTS mitigation
          efficacy updates to the relevant DOTS server. A PUT request (<xref
          target="Figure7"></xref>) is used to convey the mitigation efficacy
          update to the DOTS server.</t>

          <t>The PUT request MUST include all the parameters used in the PUT
          request to convey the DOTS signal (<xref target="post"></xref>)
          unchanged apart from the lifetime parameter value. If this is not
          the case, the DOTS server MUST reject the request with a 4.02 error
          response code.</t>

          <t>The If-Match Option (Section 5.10.8.1 of <xref
          target="RFC7252"></xref>) with an empty value is used to make the
          PUT request conditional on the current existence of the mitigation
          request. If UDP is used as transport, CoAP requests may arrive
          out-of-order. For example, the DOTS client may send a PUT request to
          convey an efficacy update to the DOTS server followed by a DELETE
          request to withdraw the mitigation request, but the DELETE request
          arrives at the DOTS server before the PUT request. To handle
          out-of-order delivery of requests, if an If-Match option is present
          in the PUT request and the 'mitigation-id' in the request matches a
          mitigation request from that DOTS client, then the request is
          processed. If no match is found, the PUT request is silently
          ignored.</t>

          <figure anchor="Figure7" title="Efficacy Update">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[   Header: PUT (Code=0.03)
   Uri-Host: "host" 
   Uri-Path: ".well-known"
   Uri-Path: "dots"
   Uri-Path: "version"
   Uri-Path: "mitigate"
   Content-Format: "application/cbor"
   If-Match: 
   {
    "mitigation-scope": {
      "client-identifier": [
         "string"
      ],
      "scope": [
        {
          "mitigation-id": integer,  
          "target-ip": [
             "string"
           ],
          "target-port-range": [
             {
               "lower-port": integer,
               "upper-port": integer
             }
           ],     
           "target-protocol": [
             integer
           ],
           "target-fqdn": [
             "string"
           ],
           "target-uri": [
             "string"
           ],
           "alias-name": [
             "string"
           ],
          "lifetime": integer,
          "attack-status": integer
        }
      ]
    }
   }
]]></artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>The 'attack-status' parameter is a mandatory attribute when doing
          a efficacy update. The various possible values contained in the
          'attack-status' parameter are described in <xref
          target="astatus"></xref>.</t>

          <texttable anchor="astatus" style="all"
                     title=" Values of 'attack-status' parameter">
            <ttcol align="right">Parameter value</ttcol>

            <ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>

            <c>1</c>

            <c>The DOTS client determines that it is still under attack.</c>

            <c>2</c>

            <c>The DOTS client determines that the attack is successfully
            mitigated (e.g., attack traffic is not seen).</c>
          </texttable>

          <t>The DOTS server indicates the result of processing a PUT request
          using CoAP response codes. The response code 2.04 (Changed) is
          returned if the DOTS server has accepted the mitigation efficacy
          update. The error response code 5.03 (Service Unavailable) is
          returned if the DOTS server has erred or is incapable of performing
          the mitigation.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sigconfig"
               title="DOTS Signal Channel Session Configuration">
        <t>The DOTS client can negotiate, configure, and retrieve the DOTS
        signal channel session behavior. The DOTS signal channel can be used,
        for example, to configure the following:<list style="letters">
            <t>Heartbeat interval: DOTS agents regularly send heartbeats (CoAP
            Ping/Pong) to each other after mutual authentication in order to
            keep the DOTS signal channel open, heartbeat messages are
            exchanged between the DOTS agents every heartbeat-interval seconds
            to detect the current status of the DOTS signal channel
            session.</t>

            <t>Missing heartbeats allowed: This variable indicates the maximum
            number of consecutive heartbeat messages for which a DOTS agent
            did not receive a response before concluding that the session is
            disconnected or defunct.</t>

            <t>Acceptable signal loss ratio: Maximum retransmissions,
            retransmission timeout value and other message transmission
            parameters for the DOTS signal channel.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Reliability is provided to requests and responses by marking them
        as Confirmable (CON) messages. DOTS signal channel session
        configuration requests and responses are marked as Confirmable (CON)
        messages. As explained in Section 2.1 of <xref
        target="RFC7252"></xref>, a Confirmable message is retransmitted using
        a default timeout and exponential back-off between retransmissions,
        until the DOTS server sends an Acknowledgement message (ACK) with the
        same Message ID conveyed from the DOTS client. Message transmission
        parameters are defined in Section 4.8 of <xref
        target="RFC7252"></xref>. Reliability is provided to the responses by
        marking them as Confirmable (CON) messages. The DOTS server can either
        piggyback the response in the acknowledgement message or if the DOTS
        server is not able to respond immediately to a request carried in a
        Confirmable message, it simply responds with an Empty Acknowledgement
        message so that the DOTS client can stop retransmitting the request.
        Empty Acknowledgement message is explained in Section 2.2 of <xref
        target="RFC7252"></xref>. When the response is ready, the server sends
        it in a new Confirmable message which then in turn needs to be
        acknowledged by the DOTS client (see Sections 5.2.1 and 5.2.2 of <xref
        target="RFC7252"></xref>). Requests and responses exchanged between
        DOTS agents during peacetime are marked as Confirmable messages.</t>

        <t>Implementation Note: A DOTS client that receives a response in a
        CON message may want to clean up the message state right after sending
        the ACK. If that ACK is lost and the DOTS server retransmits the CON,
        the DOTS client may no longer have any state to which to correlate
        this response, making the retransmission an unexpected message; the
        DOTS client will send a Reset message so it does not receive any more
        retransmissions. This behavior is normal and not an indication of an
        error (see Section 5.3.2 of <xref target="RFC7252"></xref> for more
        details).</t>

        <section anchor="discovery" title="Discover Configuration Parameters">
          <t>A GET request is used to obtain acceptable and current
          configuration parameters on the DOTS server for DOTS signal channel
          session configuration. <xref target="Figure18"></xref> shows how to
          obtain acceptable configuration parameters for the DOTS server.</t>

          <figure anchor="Figure18" title="GET to retrieve configuration">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[  Header: GET (Code=0.01)
  Uri-Host: "host" 
  Uri-Path: ".well-known"
  Uri-Path: "dots"
  Uri-Path: "version"
  Uri-Path: "config"
]]></artwork>
          </figure>

          <t></t>

          <t>The DOTS server in the 2.05 (Content) response conveys the
          current, minimum and maximum attribute values acceptable by the DOTS
          server.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="Figure19" title="GET response body">
              <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[  Content-Format: "application/cbor"
   {
     "heartbeat-interval": {
                            "CurrentValue": integer,
                            "MinValue": integer, 
                            "MaxValue" : integer, 
                           },
     "missing-hb-allowed": {
                            "CurrentValue": integer,
                            "MinValue": integer, 
                            "MaxValue" : integer, 
                           },
     "max-retransmit":     {
                            "CurrentValue": integer,
                            "MinValue": integer, 
                            "MaxValue" : integer, 
                           },
     "ack-timeout":        {
                            "CurrentValue": integer,
                            "MinValue": integer, 
                            "MaxValue" : integer, 
                           },
     "ack-random-factor":  {
                            "CurrentValue": number,
                            "MinValue": number, 
                            "MaxValue" : number, 
                           },
     "trigger-mitigation": {
                            "CurrentValue": boolean,
                           }
    }
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t><xref target="Figure17"></xref> shows an example of acceptable
          and current configuration parameters on the DOTS server for DOTS
          signal channel session configuration.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="Figure17" title="Configuration response body">
              <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[  Content-Format: "application/cbor"
  {
    "heartbeat-interval": {
                            "CurrentValue": 30,
                            "MinValue": 15, 
                            "MaxValue" : 240, 
                           },
     "missing-hb-allowed": {
                            "CurrentValue": 5,
                            "MinValue": 3, 
                            "MaxValue" : 9, 
                           },
     "max-retransmit":     {
                            "CurrentValue": 3,
                            "MinValue": 2, 
                            "MaxValue" : 15, 
                           },
     "ack-timeout":        {
                            "CurrentValue": 2,
                            "MinValue": 1, 
                            "MaxValue" : 30, 
                           },
     "ack-random-factor": {
                            "CurrentValue": 1.5,
                            "MinValue": 1.1, 
                            "MaxValue" : 4.0, 
                           },
     "trigger-mitigation": {
                            "CurrentValue": true,
                           }
  }
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Convey DOTS Signal Channel Session Configuration">
          <t>A PUT request is used to convey the configuration parameters for
          the signal channel (e.g., heartbeat interval, maximum
          retransmissions). Message transmission parameters for CoAP are
          defined in Section 4.8 of <xref target="RFC7252"></xref>. The
          RECOMMENDED values of transmission parameter values are ack_timeout
          (2 seconds), max-retransmit (3), ack-random-factor (1.5). In
          addition to those parameters, the RECOMMENDED specific DOTS
          transmission parameter values are heartbeat-interval (30 seconds)
          and missing-hb-allowed (5).<list style="empty">
              <t>Note: heartbeat-interval should be tweaked to also assist
              DOTS messages for NAT traversal (SIG-010 of <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"></xref>). According to <xref
              target="RFC8085"></xref>, keepalive messages must not be sent
              more frequently than once every 15 seconds and should use longer
              intervals when possible. Furthermore, <xref
              target="RFC4787"></xref> recommends NATs to use a state timeout
              of 2 minutes or longer, but experience shows that sending
              packets every 15 to 30 seconds is necessary to prevent the
              majority of middleboxes from losing state for UDP flows. From
              that standpoint, this specification recommends a minimum
              heartbeat-interval of 15 seconds and a maximum
              heartbeat-interval of 240 seconds. The recommended value of 30
              seconds is selected to anticipate the expiry of NAT state.</t>

              <t>A heartbeat-interval of 30 second may be seen as too chatty
              in some deployments. For such deployments, DOTS agents may
              negotiate longer heartbeat-interval values to avoid overloading
              the network with too frequent keepalives.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>When a confirmable "CoAP ping" is sent, and if there is no
          response, the "CoAP ping" will get retransmitted max-retransmit
          number of times by the CoAP layer using an initial timeout set to a
          random duration between ack_timeout and
          (ack-timeout*ack-random-factor) and exponential back-off between
          retransmissions. By choosing the recommended transmission
          parameters, the "CoAP ping" will timeout after 45 seconds. If the
          DOTS agent does not receive any response from the peer DOTS agent
          for missing-hb-allowed number of consecutive "CoAP ping" confirmable
          messages, then it concludes that the DOTS signal channel session is
          disconnected. A DOTS client MUST NOT transmit a "CoAP ping" while
          waiting for the previous "CoAP ping" response from the same DOTS
          server.</t>

          <t>If the DOTS agent wishes to change the default values of message
          transmission parameters, then it should follow the guidance given in
          Section 4.8.1 of <xref target="RFC7252"></xref>. The DOTS agents
          MUST use the negotiated values for message transmission parameters
          and default values for non-negotiated message transmission
          parameters.</t>

          <t>The signal channel session configuration is applicable to a
          single DOTS signal channel session between the DOTS agents.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="Figure13"
              title="PUT to convey the DOTS signal channel session configuration data.">
              <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[  Header: PUT (Code=0.03)
  Uri-Host: "host" 
  Uri-Path: ".well-known"
  Uri-Path: "dots"
  Uri-Path: "version"
  Uri-Path: "config"
  Content-Format: "application/cbor"
  {
   "signal-config": {
     "session-id": integer,
     "heartbeat-interval": integer,
     "missing-hb-allowed": integer,
     "max-retransmit": integer,
     "ack-timeout": integer,
     "ack-random-factor": number
     "trigger-mitigation": boolean
   }
  }
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>The parameters are described below:</t>

          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="session-id:">Identifier for the DOTS signal channel
              session configuration data represented as an integer. This
              identifier MUST be generated by the DOTS client. This document
              does not make any assumption about how this identifier is
              generated. This is a mandatory attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="heartbeat-interval: ">Time interval in seconds
              between two consecutive heartbeat messages. This is an optional
              attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="missing-hb-allowed: ">Maximum number of consecutive
              heartbeat messages for which the DOTS agent did not receive a
              response before concluding that the session is disconnected.
              This is an optional attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="max-retransmit: ">Maximum number of retransmissions
              for a message (referred to as MAX_RETRANSMIT parameter in CoAP).
              This is an optional attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="ack-timeout: ">Timeout value in seconds used to
              calculate the initial retransmission timeout value (referred to
              as ACK_TIMEOUT parameter in CoAP). This is an optional
              attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="ack-random-factor: ">Random factor used to
              influence the timing of retransmissions (referred to as
              ACK_RANDOM_FACTOR parameter in CoAP). This is an optional
              attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="trigger-mitigation: ">If the parameter value is set
              to 'false', then DDoS mitigation is triggered only when the DOTS
              signal channel session is lost. Automated mitigation on loss of
              signal is discussed in Section 3.3.3 of <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-dots-architecture"></xref>. If the DOTS client
              ceases to respond to heartbeat messages, then the DOTS server
              can detect that the DOTS session is lost. The default value of
              the parameter is 'true'. This is an optional attribute.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>In the PUT request at least one of the attributes
          heartbeat-interval, missing-hb-allowed, max-retransmit, ack-timeout,
          ack-random-factor, and trigger-mitigation MUST be present. The PUT
          request with higher numeric session-id value over-rides the DOTS
          signal channel session configuration data installed by a PUT request
          with a lower numeric session-id value.</t>

          <t><xref target="Figure14"></xref> shows a PUT request example to
          convey the configuration parameters for the DOTS signal channel.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="Figure14"
              title="PUT to convey the configuration parameters">
              <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[  Header: PUT (Code=0.03)
  Uri-Host: "www.example.com" 
  Uri-Path: ".well-known"
  Uri-Path: "dots"
  Uri-Path: "v1"
  Uri-Path: "config"
  Content-Format: "application/cbor"
  {
    "signal-config": {
     "session-id": 1234534333242,
     "heartbeat-interval": 91,
     "missing-hb-allowed": 3, 
     "max-retransmit": 7,
     "ack-timeout": 5,
     "ack-random-factor": 1.5,
     "trigger-mitigation": false
    } 
  }
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>The DOTS server indicates the result of processing the PUT
          request using CoAP response codes:<list style="symbols">
              <t>If the DOTS server finds the 'session-id' parameter value
              conveyed in the PUT request in its configuration data and if the
              DOTS server has accepted the updated configuration parameters,
              then 2.04 (Changed) code is returned in the response.</t>

              <t>If the DOTS server does not find the 'session-id' parameter
              value conveyed in the PUT request in its configuration data and
              if the DOTS server has accepted the configuration parameters,
              then a response code 2.01 (Created) is returned in the
              response.</t>

              <t>If the request is missing one or more mandatory attributes,
              then 4.00 (Bad Request) is returned in the response.</t>

              <t>If the request contains one or more invalid or unknown
              parameters, then 4.02 (Invalid query) code is returned in the
              response.</t>

              <t>Response code 4.22 (Unprocessable Entity) is returned in the
              response, if any of the heartbeat-interval, missing-hb-allowed,
              max-retransmit, target-protocol, ack-timeout, and
              ack-random-factor attribute values are not acceptable to the
              DOTS server. Upon receipt of the 4.22 error response code, the
              DOTS client should request the maximum and minimum attribute
              values acceptable to the DOTS server (<xref
              target="discovery"></xref>). The DOTS client may re-try and send
              the PUT request with updated attribute values acceptable to the
              DOTS server.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Delete DOTS Signal Channel Session Configuration">
          <t>A DELETE request is used to delete the installed DOTS signal
          channel session configuration data (<xref
          target="Figure15"></xref>).</t>

          <figure anchor="Figure15" title="DELETE configuration">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[  Header: DELETE (Code=0.04)
  Uri-Host: "host" 
  Uri-Path: ".well-known"
  Uri-Path: "dots"
  Uri-Path: "version"
  Uri-Path: "config"
  Content-Format: "application/cbor"
]]></artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>The DOTS server resets the DOTS signal channel session
          configuration back to the default values and acknowledges a DOTS
          client's request to remove the DOTS signal channel session
          configuration using 2.02 (Deleted) response code.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Redirected Signaling">
        <t>Redirected DOTS signaling is discussed in detail in Section 3.2.2
        of <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-architecture"></xref>.</t>

        <t>If a DOTS server wants to redirect a DOTS client to an alternative
        DOTS server for a signal session, then the response code 3.00
        (alternate server) will be returned in the response to the client. The
        DOTS server can return the error response code 3.00 in response to a
        PUT request from the DOTS client or convey the error response code
        3.00 in a unidirectional notification response from the DOTS
        server.</t>

        <t>The DOTS server in the error response conveys the alternate DOTS
        server FQDN, and the alternate DOTS server IP addresses and time to
        live values in the CBOR body.</t>

        <figure anchor="Figure20" title="Error response body">
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[{ 
    "alt-server": "string",
    "alt-server-record": [
      {
        "addr": "string",   
        "ttl" : integer,                    
      }
    ]
}]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The parameters are described below:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="alt-server:">FQDN of an alternate DOTS server.</t>

            <t hangText="addr:">IP address of an alternate DOTS server.</t>

            <t hangText="ttl:">Time to live (TTL) represented as an integer
            number of seconds.</t>
          </list><xref target="Figure21"></xref> shows a 3.00 response example
        to convey the DOTS alternate server www.example-alt.com, its IP
        addresses 2001:db8:6401::1 and 2001:db8:6401::2, and TTL values 3600
        and 1800.</t>

        <t><figure anchor="Figure21" title="Example of error response body">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[{
 
    "alt-server": "www.example-alt.com",
    "alt-server-record": [
      {
        "ttl" :  3600,        
        "addr": "2001:db8:6401::1"         
      },
      {
        "ttl" :  1800,        
        "addr": "2001:db8:6401::2"         
      }
    ]
}]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>When the DOTS client receives 3.00 response, it considers the
        current request as having failed, but SHOULD try the request with the
        alternate DOTS server. During a DDOS attack, the DNS server may be
        subjected to DDOS attack, alternate DOTS server IP addresses conveyed
        in the 3.00 response help the DOTS client to skip DNS lookup of the
        alternate DOTS server and can try to establish UDP or TCP session with
        the alternate DOTS server IP addresses. The DOTS client SHOULD
        implement DNS64 function to handle the scenario where IPv6-only DOTS
        client communicates with IPv4-only alternate DOTS server.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="hb" title="Heartbeat Mechanism">
        <t>To provide a metric of signal health and distinguish an 'idle'
        signal channel from a 'disconnected' or 'defunct' session, the DOTS
        agent sends a heartbeat over the signal channel to maintain its half
        of the channel. The DOTS agent similarly expects a heartbeat from its
        peer DOTS agent, and may consider a session terminated in the extended
        absence of a peer agent heartbeat.</t>

        <t>While the communication between the DOTS agents is quiescent, the
        DOTS client will probe the DOTS server to ensure it has maintained
        cryptographic state and vice versa. Such probes can also keep alive
        firewall and/or NAT bindings. This probing reduces the frequency of
        establishing a new handshake when a DOTS signal needs to be conveyed
        to the DOTS server.</t>

        <t>In case of a volumetric DDoS attack saturating the incoming link to
        the DOTS client, all traffic from the DOTS server to the DOTS client
        will likely be dropped, although the DOTS server receives heartbeat
        requests and DOTS messages from the DOTS client. In this scenario, the
        DOTS agents MUST behave differently to handle message transmission and
        DOTS session liveliness during link saturation:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>The DOTS client MUST NOT consider the DOTS session terminated
            even after maximum "missing-hb-allowed" threshold is reached. The
            DOTS client SHOULD continue to use the current DOTS session, and
            send heartbeat requests over the current DOTS session, so the DOTS
            server knows the DOTS client has not disconnected the DOTS
            session. After the maximum "missing-hb-allowed" threshold is
            reached, the DOTS client SHOULD try (D)TLS session resumption. The
            DOTS client SHOULD send mitigation requests over the current DOTS
            session, and in parallel, try (D)TLS session resumption or 0-RTT
            mode in DTLS 1.3 to piggyback the mitigation request in the
            ClientHello message. Once the link is no longer statured, if
            traffic from the DOTS server reaches the DOTS client over the
            current DOTS session, the DOTS client can stop (D)TLS session
            resumption or if (D)TLS session resumption is successful then
            disconnect the current DOTS session.</t>

            <t>If the DOTS server does not receive any traffic from the peer
            DOTS client, then the DOTS server sends heartbeat requests to the
            DOTS client and after maximum "missing-hb-allowed" threshold is
            reached, the DOTS server concludes the session is
            disconnected.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>In DOTS over UDP, heartbeat messages may be exchanged between the
        DOTS agents using the &ldquo;COAP ping&rdquo; mechanism defined in
        Section 4.2 of <xref target="RFC7252"></xref>. Concretely, the DOTS
        agent sends an Empty Confirmable message and the peer DOTS agent will
        respond by sending an Reset message.</t>

        <t>In DOTS over TCP, heartbeat messages can be exchanged between the
        DOTS agents using the Ping and Pong messages specified in Section 4.4
        of <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-coap-tcp-tls"></xref>. That is, the
        DOTS agent sends a Ping message and the peer DOTS agent would respond
        by sending a single Pong message.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="YANG" title="DOTS Signal Channel YANG Modules">
      <t>This document defines YANG <xref target="RFC7950"></xref> modules for
      mitigation scope and DOTS signal channel session configuration data.</t>

      <section title="Mitigation Request YANG Module Tree Structure">
        <t>This document defines the YANG module "ietf-dots-signal" (<xref
        target="yrequest"></xref>), which has the following tree
        structure:<figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[module: ietf-dots-signal
    +--rw mitigation-scope
       +--rw client-identifier*   binary
       +--rw scope* [mitigation-id]
          +--rw mitigation-id        int32
          +--rw target-ip*           inet:ip-address
          +--rw target-prefix*       inet:ip-prefix
          +--rw target-port-range* [lower-port upper-port]
          |  +--rw lower-port    inet:port-number
          |  +--rw upper-port    inet:port-number
          +--rw target-protocol*     uint8
          +--rw target-fqdn*         inet:domain-name
          +--rw target-uri*          inet:uri
          +--rw alias-name*          string
          +--rw lifetime?            int32
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="yrequest" title="Mitigation Request YANG Module ">
        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[<CODE BEGINS> file "ietf-dots-signal@2017-11-27.yang"

module ietf-dots-signal {
      yang-version 1.1;
      namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-dots-signal";
      prefix "signal";

      import ietf-inet-types {
          prefix "inet";
      }

    organization "IETF DOTS Working Group";

    contact
      "Konda, Tirumaleswar Reddy <TirumaleswarReddy_Konda@McAfee.com>
       Mohamed Boucadair <mohamed.boucadair@orange.com>
       Prashanth Patil <praspati@cisco.com>
       Andrew Mortensen <amortensen@arbor.net>
       Nik Teague <nteague@verisign.com>";

     description
       "This module contains YANG definition for DOTS
        signal sent by the DOTS client to the DOTS server.

        Copyright (c) 2017 IETF Trust and the persons identified as
        authors of the code.  All rights reserved.

        Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
        without modification, is permitted pursuant to, and subject
        to the license terms contained in, the Simplified BSD License
        set forth in Section 4.c of the IETF Trust's Legal Provisions
        Relating to IETF Documents
        (http://trustee.ietf.org/license-info).

        This version of this YANG module is part of RFC XXXX; see
        the RFC itself for full legal notices.";

     revision 2017-11-27 {
       description
         "Initial revision.";
       reference
         "RFC XXXX: A Distributed Denial-of-Service Open Threat 
                    Signaling (DOTS) Signal Channel";
     }

     container mitigation-scope {
          description 
             "Specifies the scope of the mitigation request.";
          
          leaf-list client-identifier {
             type binary; 
             description             
               "The client identifier may be conveyed by 
                the DOTS gateway to propagate the DOTS client
                identity from the gateway's client-side to the
                gateway's server-side, and from the gateway's
                server-side to the DOTS server. 

                It allows the final DOTS server to accept
                mitigation requests with scopes which the DOTS
                client is authorized to manage.";
          }

          list scope {
             key mitigation-id;
             description 
               "The scope of the request.";

             leaf mitigation-id {
                type int32;
                description 
                  "Mitigation request identifier. 
           
                  This identifier must be unique for each mitigation
                  request bound to the DOTS client.";
              }

              leaf-list target-ip {
                  type inet:ip-address;
                  description 
                    "IPv4 or IPv6 address identifying the target.";
              }

              leaf-list target-prefix {
                  type inet:ip-prefix;
                  description 
                    "IPv4 or IPv6 prefix identifying the target.";
              }

              list target-port-range {
                  key "lower-port upper-port";

                  description 
                    "Port range. When only lower-port is  
                     present, it represents a single port.";

                  leaf lower-port {
                     type inet:port-number;
                     mandatory true; 
                     description "Lower port number.";
                  }

                  leaf upper-port {
                     type inet:port-number;
                       must ". >= ../lower-port" {
                         error-message
                           "The upper port number must be greater than  
                            or equal to lower port number.";
                       }
                     description "Upper port number.";
                  }
              }

              leaf-list target-protocol {
                  type uint8;
                  description 
                    "Identifies the target protocol number.

                     The value '0' means 'all protocols'.
               
                     Values are taken from the IANA protocol registry:
                     https://www.iana.org/assignments/protocol-numbers/
                     protocol-numbers.xhtml

                     For example, 6 for a TCP or 17 for UDP.";
              }

              leaf-list target-fqdn {
                   type inet:domain-name;
                   description "FQDN";
              }

              leaf-list target-uri {
                  type inet:uri;
                  description "URI";
              }

              leaf-list alias-name {
                  type string;
                  description "alias name";
              }

              leaf lifetime {
                  type int32;
                  units "seconds";
                  default 3600;
                  description 
                    "Indicates the lifetime of the mitigation request.";
              }
          } 
     }
  }
<CODE ENDS>]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Session Configuration YANG Module Tree Structure">
        <t>This document defines the YANG module "ietf-dots-signal-config"
        (<xref target="config"></xref>), which has the following
        structure:<figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[module: ietf-dots-signal-config
    +--rw signal-config
       +--rw session-id?           int32
       +--rw heartbeat-interval?   int16
       +--rw missing-hb-allowed?   int16
       +--rw max-retransmit?       int16
       +--rw ack-timeout?          int16
       +--rw ack-random-factor?    decimal64
       +--rw trigger-mitigation?   boolean]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="config" title="Session Configuration YANG Module ">
        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[<CODE BEGINS> file "ietf-dots-signal-config@2017-11-27.yang"

module ietf-dots-signal-config {
     yang-version 1.1;
     namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-dots-signal-config";
     prefix "config";

    organization "IETF DOTS Working Group";

    contact 
      "Konda, Tirumaleswar Reddy <TirumaleswarReddy_Konda@McAfee.com>
       Mohamed Boucadair <mohamed.boucadair@orange.com>
       Prashanth Patil <praspati@cisco.com>
       Andrew Mortensen <amortensen@arbor.net>
       Nik Teague <nteague@verisign.com>";

     description
       "This module contains YANG definition for DOTS
        signal channel session configuration.

        Copyright (c) 2017 IETF Trust and the persons identified as
        authors of the code.  All rights reserved.

        Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
        without modification, is permitted pursuant to, and subject
        to the license terms contained in, the Simplified BSD License
        set forth in Section 4.c of the IETF Trust's Legal Provisions
        Relating to IETF Documents
        (http://trustee.ietf.org/license-info).

        This version of this YANG module is part of RFC XXXX; see
        the RFC itself for full legal notices.";

     revision 2017-11-27 {
       description
         "Initial revision.";
       reference
         "RFC XXXX: A Distributed Denial-of-Service Open Threat 
                    Signaling (DOTS) Signal Channel";
     }

     container signal-config {
          description 
            "DOTS signal channel session configuration.";

          leaf session-id {
              type int32;
              description 
                "An identifier for the DOTS signal channel 
                 session configuration data.";
          }

          leaf heartbeat-interval {
              type int16;
              units "seconds";
              default 30;
              description 
                "DOTS agents regularly send heartbeats to each other 
                 after mutual authentication in order to keep
                 the DOTS signal channel open.";
          }

          leaf missing-hb-allowed {
              type int16;
              default 5;
              description 
                "Maximum number of missing heartbeats allowed.";
          }

          leaf max-retransmit {
              type int16;
              default 3;
              description 
                "Maximum number of retransmissions of a 
                 Confirmable message.";
          }

          leaf ack-timeout {
              type int16;
              units "seconds";
              default 2;
              description 
                 "Initial retransmission timeout value.";
          }

          leaf ack-random-factor {
              type decimal64 {
                fraction-digits 2;
              }
             default 1.5;
             description 
               "Random factor used to influence the timing of
                retransmissions.";
         }
         leaf trigger-mitigation {
             type boolean;
             default true;
             description 
               "If false, then mitigation is triggered 
                only when the DOTS server channel session is lost";
         }
      }
}
<CODE ENDS>]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="mapping" title="Mapping Parameters to CBOR">
      <t>All parameters in the payload in the DOTS signal channel MUST be
      mapped to CBOR types as shown in Table 4 and are given an integer key to
      save space. The recipient of the payload MAY reject the information if
      it is not suitably mapped.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[/--------------------+---------------------+--------------------------\
| Parameter name     | CBOR key            | CBOR major type of value |
+--------------------+---------------------+--------------------------+
| mitigation-scope   | 1                   | 5 (map)                  |
| scope              | 2                   | 5 (map)                  |
| mitigation-id      | 3                   | 0 (unsigned)             |
| target-ip          | 4                   | 4 (array)                |
| target-port-range  | 5                   | 4                        |
| lower-port         | 6                   | 0                        |
| upper-port         | 7                   | 0                        |
| target-protocol    | 8                   | 4                        |
| target-fqdn        | 9                   | 4                        |
| target-uri         | 10                  | 4                        |
| alias-name         | 11                  | 4                        |
| lifetime           | 12                  | 0                        |
| attack-status      | 13                  | 0                        |
| signal-config      | 14                  | 5                        |
| heartbeat-interval | 15                  | 0                        |
| max-retransmit     | 16                  | 0                        |
| ack-timeout        | 17                  | 0                        |
| ack-random-factor  | 18                  | 7                        |
| MinValue           | 19                  | 0                        |
| MaxValue           | 20                  | 0                        |
| status             | 21                  | 0                        |
| bytes-dropped      | 22                  | 0                        |
| bps-dropped        | 23                  | 0                        |
| pkts-dropped       | 24                  | 0                        |
| pps-dropped        | 25                  | 0                        |
| session-id         | 26                  | 0                        |
| trigger-mitigation | 27                  | 7 (simple types)         |
| missing-hb-allowed | 28                  | 0                        |
| CurrentValue       | 29                  | 0                        |
| mitigation-start   | 30                  | 7 (floating-point)       |
| target-prefix      | 31                  | 4 (array)                |
| client-identifier  | 32                  | 2 (byte string)          |
| alt-server         | 33                  | 2                        |
| alt-server-record  | 34                  | 4                        |
| addr               | 35                  | 2                        |
| ttl                | 36                  | 0                        |
\--------------------+---------------------+--------------------------/
     Table 4: CBOR mappings used in DOTS signal channel message
]]></artwork>

          <!---->
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section title="(D)TLS Protocol Profile and Performance Considerations">
      <section title="(D)TLS Protocol Profile">
        <t>This section defines the (D)TLS protocol profile of DOTS signal
        channel over (D)TLS and DOTS data channel over TLS.</t>

        <t>There are known attacks on (D)TLS, such as machine-in-the-middle
        and protocol downgrade. These are general attacks on (D)TLS and not
        specific to DOTS over (D)TLS; please refer to the (D)TLS RFCs for
        discussion of these security issues. DOTS agents MUST adhere to the
        (D)TLS implementation recommendations and security considerations of
        <xref target="RFC7525"></xref> except with respect to (D)TLS version.
        Since encryption of DOTS using (D)TLS is virtually a green-field
        deployment DOTS agents MUST implement only (D)TLS 1.2 or later.</t>

        <t>When a DOTS client is configured with a domain name of the DOTS
        server, and connects to its configured DOTS server, the server may
        present it with a PKIX certificate. In order to ensure proper
        authentication, DOTS client MUST verify the entire certification path
        per <xref target="RFC5280"></xref>. The DOTS client additionaly uses
        <xref target="RFC6125"></xref> validation techniques to compare the
        domain name to the certificate provided.</t>

        <t>A key challenge to deploying DOTS is provisioning DOTS clients,
        including the distribution of keying material to DOTS clients to make
        possible the required mutual authentication of DOTS agents. EST
        defines a method of certificate enrollment by which domains operating
        DOTS servers may provision DOTS clients with all necessary
        cryptographic keying material, including a private key and certificate
        with which to authenticate itself. One deployment option is DOTS
        clients to behave as EST clients for certificate enrollment from an
        EST server provisioned by the mitigation provider. This document does
        not specify which EST mechanism the DOTS client uses to achieve
        initial enrollment.</t>

        <t>Implementations compliant with this profile MUST implement all of
        the following items:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>DTLS record replay detection (Section 3.3 of <xref
            target="RFC6347"></xref>) to protect against replay attacks.</t>

            <t>(D)TLS session resumption without server-side state <xref
            target="RFC5077"></xref> to resume session and convey the DOTS
            signal.</t>

            <t>Raw public keys <xref target="RFC7250"></xref> or PSK handshake
            <xref target="RFC4279"></xref> which reduce the size of the
            ServerHello, and can be used by DOTS agents that cannot obtain
            certificates (e.g., DOTS clients and DOTS gateways on private
            networks).</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Implementations compliant with this profile SHOULD implement all of
        the following items to reduce the delay required to deliver a DOTS
        signal:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>TLS False Start <xref target="RFC7918"></xref> which reduces
            round-trips by allowing the TLS second flight of messages
            (ChangeCipherSpec) to also contain the DOTS signal.</t>

            <t>Cached Information Extension <xref target="RFC7924"></xref>
            which avoids transmitting the server's certificate and certificate
            chain if the client has cached that information from a previous
            TLS handshake.</t>

            <t>TCP Fast Open <xref target="RFC7413"></xref> can reduce the
            number of round-trips to convey DOTS signal.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="mtu" title="MTU and Fragmentation">
        <t>To avoid DOTS signal message fragmentation and the consequently
        decreased probability of message delivery, DOTS agents MUST ensure
        that the DTLS record MUST fit within a single datagram. If the path
        MTU is not known to the DOTS server, an IP MTU of 1280 bytes SHOULD be
        assumed. The length of the URL MUST NOT exceed 256 bytes. If UDP is
        used to convey the DOTS signal messages then the DOTS client must
        consider the amount of record expansion expected by the DTLS
        processing when calculating the size of CoAP message that fits within
        the path MTU. Path MTU MUST be greater than or equal to [CoAP message
        size + DTLS overhead of 13 octets + authentication overhead of the
        negotiated DTLS cipher suite + block padding (Section 4.1.1.1 of <xref
        target="RFC6347"></xref>). If the request size exceeds the path MTU
        then the DOTS client MUST split the DOTS signal into separate
        messages, for example the list of addresses in the 'target-ip'
        parameter could be split into multiple lists and each list conveyed in
        a new PUT request.</t>

        <t>Implementation Note: DOTS choice of message size parameters works
        well with IPv6 and with most of today's IPv4 paths. However, with
        IPv4, it is harder to absolutely ensure that there is no IP
        fragmentation. If IPv4 support on unusual networks is a consideration
        and path MTU is unknown, implementations may want to limit themselves
        to more conservative IPv4 datagram sizes such as 576 bytes, as per
        <xref target="RFC0791"></xref> IP packets up to 576 bytes should never
        need to be fragmented, thus sending a maximum of 500 bytes of DOTS
        signal over a UDP datagram will generally avoid IP fragmentation.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="DTLS" title="(D)TLS 1.3 Considerations">
      <t>TLS 1.3 <xref target="I-D.ietf-tls-tls13"></xref> provides critical
      latency improvements for connection establishment over TLS 1.2. The DTLS
      1.3 protocol <xref target="I-D.rescorla-tls-dtls13"></xref> is based on
      the TLS 1.3 protocol and provides equivalent security guarantees. (D)TLS
      1.3 provides two basic handshake modes of interest to DOTS signal
      channel:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Absent packet loss, a full handshake in which the DOTS client is
          able to send the DOTS signal message after one round trip and the
          DOTS server immediately after receiving the first DOTS signal
          message from the client.</t>

          <t>0-RTT mode in which the DOTS client can authenticate itself and
          send DOTS signal message on its first flight, thus reducing
          handshake latency. 0-RTT only works if the DOTS client has
          previously communicated with that DOTS server, which is very likely
          with the DOTS signal channel. The DOTS client SHOULD establish a
          (D)TLS session with the DOTS server during peacetime and share a
          PSK. During DDOS attack, the DOTS client can use the (D)TLS session
          to convey the DOTS signal message and if there is no response from
          the server after multiple re-tries then the DOTS client can resume
          the (D)TLS session in 0-RTT mode using PSK. A simplified TLS 1.3
          handshake with 0-RTT DOTS signal message exchange is shown in <xref
          target="Figure24"></xref>.<figure anchor="Figure24"
              title="TLS 1.3 handshake with 0-RTT">
              <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[       DOTS Client                                    DOTS Server

      ClientHello
      (Finished)
      (0-RTT DOTS signal message)
      (end_of_early_data)        -------->
                                                     ServerHello
                                            {EncryptedExtensions}
                                            {ServerConfiguration}
                                                    {Certificate}
                                              {CertificateVerify}
                                                       {Finished}
                                <--------   [DOTS signal message]
      {Finished}                -------->

      [DOTS signal message]     <------->   [DOTS signal message]
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="mutauth"
             title="Mutual Authentication of DOTS Agents &amp; Authorization of DOTS Clients">
      <t>(D)TLS based on client certificate can be used for mutual
      authentication between DOTS agents. If a DOTS gateway is involved, DOTS
      clients and DOTS gateway MUST perform mutual authentication; only
      authorized DOTS clients are allowed to send DOTS signals to a DOTS
      gateway. DOTS gateway and DOTS server MUST perform mutual
      authentication; DOTS server only allows DOTS signals from authorized
      DOTS gateway, creating a two-link chain of transitive authentication
      between the DOTS client and the DOTS server.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="Figure12"
          title="Example of Authentication and Authorization of DOTS Agents">
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[ +-----------------------------------------------+
 |       example.com domain         +---------+  |
 |                                  | AAA     |  |
 | +---------------+                | Server  |  |
 | | Application   |                +------+--+  |
 | | server        +<-----------------+    ^     |
 | | (DOTS client) |                  |    |     |
 | +---------------+                  |    |     |
 |                                    V    V     |    example.net domain
 |                              +-----+----+--+  |     +---------------+
 | +--------------+             |             |  |     |               |
 | |   Guest      +<-----x----->+    DOTS     +<------>+    DOTS       |
 | | (DOTS client)|             |    Gateway  |  |     |    Server     |
 | +--------------+             |             |  |     |               |
 |                              +----+--------+  |     +---------------+
 |                                   ^           |
 |                                   |           |
 | +----------------+                |           |
 | | DDOS detector  |                |           |
 | | (DOTS client)  +<---------------+           |
 | +----------------+                            |
 +-----------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>In the example depicted in <xref target="Figure12"></xref>,
      the DOTS gateway and DOTS clients within the 'example.com' domain
      mutually authenticate with each other. After the DOTS gateway validates
      the identity of a DOTS client, it communicates with the AAA server in
      the 'example.com' domain to determine if the DOTS client is authorized
      to request DDOS mitigation. If the DOTS client is not authorized, a 4.01
      (Unauthorized) is returned in the response to the DOTS client. In this
      example, the DOTS gateway only allows the application server and DDOS
      detector to request DDOS mitigation, but does not permit the user of
      type 'guest' to request DDOS mitigation.</t>

      <t>Also, DOTS gateway and DOTS server located in different domains MUST
      perform mutual authentication (e.g., using certificates). A DOTS server
      will only allow a DOTS gateway with a certificate for a particular
      domain to request mitigation for that domain. In reference to <xref
      target="Figure12"></xref>, the DOTS server only allows the DOTS gateway
      to request mitigation for 'example.com' domain and not for other
      domains.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This specification registers a default port, new URI suffix in the
      Well-Known URIs registry, new CoAP response code, new parameters for
      DOTS signal channel and establishes registries for mappings to CBOR.</t>

      <section anchor="port"
               title="DOTS Signal Channel UDP and TCP Port Number">
        <t>IANA has assigned the port number TBD to the DOTS signal channel
        protocol, for both UDP and TCP.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="uri" title="Well-Known 'dots' URI">
        <t>This memo registers the 'dots' well-known URI in the Well-Known
        URIs registry as defined by <xref target="RFC5785"></xref>.</t>

        <t>URI suffix: dots</t>

        <t>Change controller: IETF</t>

        <t>Specification document(s): This RFC</t>

        <t>Related information: None</t>
      </section>

      <section title="CoAP Response Code">
        <t>The following entry is added to the "CoAP Response Codes"
        sub-registry:</t>

        <texttable anchor="alt" title="CoAP Response Code">
          <ttcol>Code</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Description</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>

          <c>3.00</c>

          <c>Alternate server</c>

          <c>[RFCXXXX]</c>
        </texttable>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section title="DOTS Signal Channel CBOR Mappings Registry">
        <t>A new registry will be requested from IANA, entitled "DOTS signal
        channel CBOR Mappings Registry". The registry is to be created as
        Expert Review Required.</t>

        <section title="Registration Template">
          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Parameter name:"><vspace /> Parameter names (e.g.,
              "target_ip") in the DOTS signal channel.</t>

              <t hangText="CBOR Key Value:"><vspace /> Key value for the
              parameter. The key value MUST be an integer in the range of 1 to
              65536. The key values in the range of 32768 to 65536 are
              assigned for Vendor-Specific parameters.</t>

              <t hangText="CBOR Major Type:"><vspace /> CBOR Major type and
              optional tag for the claim.</t>

              <t hangText="Change Controller:"><vspace /> For Standards Track
              RFCs, list the "IESG". For others, give the name of the
              responsible party. Other details (e.g., postal address, email
              address, home page URI) may also be included.</t>

              <t hangText="Specification Document(s):"><vspace /> Reference to
              the document or documents that specify the parameter, preferably
              including URIs that can be used to retrieve copies of the
              documents. An indication of the relevant sections may also be
              included but is not required.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Initial Registry Contents ">
          <t><?rfc subcompact="yes"?> <list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: <spanx style="verb">mitigation-scope</spanx></t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 1</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 5</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: <spanx style="verb">scope</spanx></t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 2</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 5</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: <spanx style="verb">mitigation-id</spanx></t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 3</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 0</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name:target-ip</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 4</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 4</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: target-port-range</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 5</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 4</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: <spanx style="verb">lower-port</spanx></t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 6</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 0</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: <spanx style="verb">upper-port</spanx></t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 7</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 0</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: target-protocol</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 8</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 4</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: <spanx style="verb">target-fqdn</spanx></t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 9</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 4</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: <spanx style="verb">target-uri</spanx></t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 10</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 4</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: alias-name</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 11</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 4</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: <spanx style="verb">lifetime</spanx></t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 12</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 0</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: attack-status</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 13</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 0</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: signal-config</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 14</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 5</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: heartbeat-interval</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 15</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 0</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: max-retransmit</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 16</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 0</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: ack-timeout</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 17</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 0</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: ack-random-factor</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 18</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 7</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: MinValue</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 19</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 0</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: MaxValue</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 20</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 0</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: status</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 21</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 0</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: bytes-dropped</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 22</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 0</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: bps-dropped</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 23</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 0</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: pkts-dropped</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 24</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 0</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: pps-dropped</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 25</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 0</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: session-id</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 26</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 0</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: trigger-mitigation</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 27</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 7</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: missing-hb-allowed</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 28</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 0</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name: CurrentValue</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 29</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 0</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name:mitigation-start</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 30</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 7</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name:target-prefix</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 31</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 4</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list></t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name:client-identifier</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 32</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 2</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name:alt-server</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 33</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 2</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name:alt-server-record</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 34</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 4</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name:addr</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 35</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 2</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list><list style="symbols">
              <t>Parameter Name:ttl</t>

              <t>CBOR Key Value: 36</t>

              <t>CBOR Major Type: 0</t>

              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>

              <t>Specification Document(s): this document</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-IANA" title="YANG Modules">
        <t>This document requests IANA to register the following URIs in the
        "IETF XML Registry" <xref target="RFC3688"></xref>: <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[         URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-dots-signal
         Registrant Contact: The IESG.
         XML: N/A; the requested URI is an XML namespace.

         URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-dots-signal-config
         Registrant Contact: The IESG.
         XML: N/A; the requested URI is an XML namespace.
]]></artwork>
          </figure> This document requests IANA to register the following YANG
        modules in the "YANG Module Names" registry <xref
        target="RFC7950"></xref>.<figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[         name: ietf-signal
         namespace: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-dots-signal
         prefix: signal
         reference: RFC XXXX

         name: ietf-dots-signal-config
         namespace: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-dots-signal-config
         prefix: config
         reference: RFC XXXX
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Implementation Status">
      <t>[Note to RFC Editor: Please remove this section and reference to
      <xref target="RFC7942"></xref> prior to publication.]</t>

      <t>This section records the status of known implementations of the
      protocol defined by this specification at the time of posting of this
      Internet-Draft, and is based on a proposal described in <xref
      target="RFC7942"></xref>. The description of implementations in this
      section is intended to assist the IETF in its decision processes in
      progressing drafts to RFCs. Please note that the listing of any
      individual implementation here does not imply endorsement by the IETF.
      Furthermore, no effort has been spent to verify the information
      presented here that was supplied by IETF contributors. This is not
      intended as, and must not be construed to be, a catalog of available
      implementations or their features. Readers are advised to note that
      other implementations may exist.</t>

      <t>According to <xref target="RFC7942"></xref>, "this will allow
      reviewers and working groups to assign due consideration to documents
      that have the benefit of running code, which may serve as evidence of
      valuable experimentation and feedback that have made the implemented
      protocols more mature. It is up to the individual working groups to use
      this information as they see fit".</t>

      <section title="nttdots">
        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Organization: ">NTT Communication is developing a
            DOTS client and DOTS server software based on DOTS signal channel
            specified in this draft. It will be open-sourced.</t>

            <t hangText="Description: ">Early implementation of DOTS protocol.
            It is aimed to implement a full DOTS protocol spec in accordance
            with maturing of DOTS protocol itself.</t>

            <t
            hangText="Implementation: ">https://github.com/nttdots/go-dots</t>

            <t hangText="Level of maturity: ">It is a early implementation of
            DOTS protocol. Messaging between DOTS clients and DOTS servers has
            been tested. Level of maturity will increase in accordance with
            maturing of DOTS protocol itself.</t>

            <t hangText="Coverage: ">Capability of DOTS client: sending DOTS
            messages to the DOTS server in CoAP over DTLS as dots-signal.
            Capability of DOTS server: receiving dots-signal, validating
            received dots-signal, starting mitigation by handing over the
            dots-signal to DDOS mitigator.</t>

            <t hangText="Licensing: ">It will be open-sourced with BSD
            3-clause license.</t>

            <t hangText="Implementation experience: ">It is implemented in
            Go-lang. Core specification of signaling is mature to be
            implemented, however, finding good libraries(like DTLS, CoAP) is
            rather difficult.</t>

            <t hangText="Contact: ">Kaname Nishizuka
            &lt;kaname@nttv6.jp&gt;</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Authenticated encryption MUST be used for data confidentiality and
      message integrity. (D)TLS based on client certificate MUST be used for
      mutual authentication. The interaction between the DOTS agents requires
      Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS) and Transport Layer Security
      (TLS) with a cipher suite offering confidentiality protection and the
      guidance given in <xref target="RFC7525"></xref> MUST be followed to
      avoid attacks on (D)TLS.</t>

      <t>A single DOTS signal channel between DOTS agents can be used to
      exchange multiple DOTS signal messages. To reduce DOTS client and DOTS
      server workload, DOTS client SHOULD re-use the (D)TLS session.</t>

      <t>If TCP is used between DOTS agents, an attacker may be able to inject
      RST packets, bogus application segments, etc., regardless of whether TLS
      authentication is used. Because the application data is TLS protected,
      this will not result in the application receiving bogus data, but it
      will constitute a DoS on the connection. This attack can be countered by
      using TCP-AO <xref target="RFC5925"></xref>. If TCP-AO is used, then any
      bogus packets injected by an attacker will be rejected by the TCP-AO
      integrity check and therefore will never reach the TLS layer.</t>

      <t>In order to prevent leaking internal information outside a
      client-domain, DOTS gateways located in the client-domain SHOULD NOT
      reveal the identity of internal DOTS clients (client-identifier) unless
      explicitly configured to do so.</t>

      <t>Special care should be taken in order to ensure that the activation
      of the proposed mechanism won't have an impact on the stability of the
      network (including connectivity and services delivered over that
      network).</t>

      <t>Involved functional elements in the cooperation system must establish
      exchange instructions and notification over a secure and authenticated
      channel. Adequate filters can be enforced to avoid that nodes outside a
      trusted domain can inject request such as deleting filtering rules.
      Nevertheless, attacks can be initiated from within the trusted domain if
      an entity has been corrupted. Adequate means to monitor trusted nodes
      should also be enabled.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="contr" title="Contributors">
      <t>The following individuals have contributed to this document:</t>

      <t>Mike Geller Cisco Systems, Inc. 3250 Florida 33309 USA Email:
      mgeller@cisco.com</t>

      <t>Robert Moskowitz HTT Consulting Oak Park, MI 42837 United States
      Email: rgm@htt-consult.com</t>

      <t>Dan Wing Email: dwing-ietf@fuggles.com</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to Christian Jacquenet, Roland Dobbins, Roman D. Danyliw,
      Michael Richardson, Ehud Doron, Kaname Nishizuka, Dave Dolson, Liang
      Xia, Jon Shallow, and Gilbert Clark for the discussion and comments.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7525"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6347"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5246"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5925"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7252"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7250"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7641"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6234"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5785"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4279"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5280"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6125"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3688'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-core-coap-tcp-tls"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7950"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4732"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7942"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4987'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7049"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7413"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5077"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6555'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.0791'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6724'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4632"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7918"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7924"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7589"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4787'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7030'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4340'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4960'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-netmod-yang-tree-diagrams'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-tls-tls13"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-core-yang-cbor"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-core-comi"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-dots-use-cases"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-dots-architecture"
?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-dots-data-channel" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.rescorla-tls-dtls13" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8085"?>

      <reference anchor="proto_numbers"
                 target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/protocol-numbers">
        <front>
          <title>IANA, "Protocol Numbers"</title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
